A Finding Aid to the William Clutz Papers, 1930-2016, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
WIlliam Clutz papers
1930-2016
Archives of American Art
Clutz, William
AAA.clutwill
Archival Resource Key
3.1 Linear feet
11 Gigabytes
The papers of New York painter William Clutz measure 3.1 linear feet and date from 1930-2016. The collection consists of biographical material, correspondence, personal business records, printed material, photographic material, artworks, and twelve sketchbooks which illuminate the career and artistic development of Clutz, a painter known for depictions of figures in urban settings. The photographic material is particularly robust and includes hundreds of photographs, slides, transparencies, and digital images of Clutz, family, friends, his painting, as well as documentation of exhibition installations. Artwork and sketchbooks in pencil, pastel, and charcoal provide a glimpse into the preliminary stages of his work process.
Biographical / Historical
William Clutz (1933- ) is a painter and art instructor who lived in New York City from 1955-1996 and now resides in Rhinebeck, New York. He was born in Gettysburg, Pennsylvania, and later studied at the Mercersburg Academy and University of Iowa before moving to New York City. Clutz's paintings, pastels, and charcoal drawings often depict figures in urban landscapes, with light playing a key role in composition and mood. He has exhibited with a number of galleries over the past several decades including the Bertha Schaefer Gallery, Brooke Alexander Gallery, Alonzo Gallery, Tatistcheff Gallery, the Katharina Rich Perlow Gallery, and others. In addition to his career as a professional artist, Clutz taught painting and drawing at Parsons the New School for Design from 1970-1992.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated to the Archives of American Art between 1980-2016 by William Clutz.
Conditions Governing Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center. Contact Reference Services for more information.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as seven series
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1930-2015 (4 folders; Box 1)
Series 2: Correspondence, circa 1946-2015 (0.2 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 3: Personal Business Records, 1967-2015 (0.2 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 4: Printed Material, 149-2012 (0.5 linear feet; Box 1, OV 5)
Series 5: Photographic Material, circa 1940-2016 (1.2 linear feet; Box 1-2, OV 6; 11 gigabytes; ER01-ER03)
Series 6: Artwork, circa 1960-2000 (2 folders; Box 2, OV 7)
Series 7: Sketchbooks, circa 1955-1990 (0.9 linear feet; Box 2-4)
Scope and Contents
The papers of New York painter William Clutz measure 3.1 linear feet and date from 1930-2016. The collection consists of biographical material, correspondence, personal business records, printed material, photographic material, artworks, and twelve sketchbooks which illuminate the career and artistic development of Clutz, a painter known for depictions of figures in urban settings. The photographic material is particularly robust and includes hundreds of photographs, slides, transparencies, and digital images of Clutz, family, friends, his painting, as well as documentation of exhibition installations. Artwork and sketchbooks in pencil, pastel, and charcoal provide a glimpse into the preliminary stages of his work process.
Sketchbooks; Photographs; Art -- Study and teaching; Art teachers -- New York (State) -- New York; Painters -- New York (State) -- New York
- Biographical Material, 1930-2015; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 4 Folders Box 1
  Scope and Contents
  Biographical material dates from 1930-2015 and includes biographical notes, resumes, awards, as well as one folder of photographs and clippings related to his family and one related to his longtime partner, John F. Sheehy. One unpublished writing about Clutz is also filed here.
  - Biographical Notes, Diplomas, Awards, 1951-2015; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Clutz Family, 1930-1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - John F. Sheehy, circa 2000-2003; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Writing by Robert H. Luck, "William Clutz: Today's Master of the Loaded Brush", circa 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, circa 1946-2015; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 0.2 Linear feet Box 1
  Correspondence dates from circa 1946-2015 and is both personal and professional in nature. Early correspondence includes several letters Clutz wrote to his parents while in college, some describing his paintings. Professional correspondence is with galleries, museums, critics, and others regarding exhibition planning and logistic, gifts, loans, and sales. Scattered among the correspondence are contracts, loan agreements, and sales invoices.
  - Chronological Correspondence, circa 1946-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Chronological Correspondence, 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Chronological Correspondence, 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Chronological Correspondence, 1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Chronological Correspondence, circa 2000-2015; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Personal Business Records, 1967-2015; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 0.2 Linear feet Box 1
  Personal business records date from 1967-2015 and consist of documentation relating to the conservation, exhibitions, sales, gifts, and photographic reproduction of Clutz's works.
  - Conservation and Framing, 2001-2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Gifts to Museums, 1990-2015; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Katharina Rich Perlow Gallery, 1999-2012; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Receipts, Invoices, Agreements, circa 2004; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Sales, 1967-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Printed Material, 1949-2012; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 0.5 Linear feet Box 1, OV 5
  Printed material dates from 1949-2012 and documents Clutz's professional career and exhibition history through announcements, clippings, exhibition catalogs, periodicals, press releases, price lists, and other types of printed matter.
  - Announcements, 1949-2009; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Clippings, circa 1960-2012; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16-17)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1950s-2000s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18-20)
  - Periodicals, Bulletins, Pamphlets, circa 1972-1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Press Releases, 1969-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Price Lists, 1977-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Oversized Calendar, 1984; Archival Resource Key (Box OV 5)
- Photographic Material, circa 1940-2016; Series 5; Archival Resource Key; 11 Gigabytes ER01-ER03; 1.2 Linear feet Box 1-2, OV 6
  The photographic material dates from circa 1940-2016 and includes primarily photographs and digital photographs with a few slides and transparencies. One folder contains photographs of Clutz throughout all stages of his life and with family and friends. Several folders contains photographs and digital photographs of his artwork throughout his career. Exhibition and installation photographs are arranged chronologically and document Clutz's exhibitions through the decades, including those at Bertha Schaefer Gallery, Brooke Alexander Gallery, Alonzo Gallery, Tatistcheff Gallery, Katharina Rich Perlow Gallery, and others. The last folder contains a few photographs that were used as source material for a painting.
  - William Clutz, Family, Friends, circa 1940-2007; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Oversized photographs housed in OV 6
  - Artwork, Black and White Prints, circa 1950-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 25-26)
  - Artwork, Black and White Prints, circa 1950-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Artwork, Color Prints, circa 1980-2010; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2-3)
  - Artwork, Computer Printouts and Digital Photographs, Collection of David and Theresa Clutz, 2015-2016; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Includes born digital material, see ER01
  - Digital Photographs, 2015-2016; Archival Resource Key; 108 Megabytes 20 computer files (Box ER01)
  - Artwork, Computer Printouts and Digital Photographs, Portfolio, 2014; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Includes born digital material, see ER02
  - Digital Photographs, 2014; Archival Resource Key; 1.77 Gigabytes 566 computer files (Box ER02)
  - Artwork, Digital Photographs, 2004-2014; Archival Resource Key; 9.13 Gigabytes 1,136 computer files (Box ER03)
  - Artwork, Slides and Transparencies, circa 1965-2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Exhibitions and Installations, circa 1960-2013; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 8-13)
  - Source Photographs, circa 2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Oversized William Clutz Photographs from Box 1, Folder 24, Archival Resource Key (Box OV 6)
- Artwork, circa 1960-2000; Series 6; Archival Resource Key; 2 Folders Box 2, OV 7
  Artworks date from circa 1960-2000 and include sketches in pencil, charcoal, and pastel, as well as a few paintings. Some works are preliminary studies for larger works, including street scenes occupied by groups of figures, while others are casual subjects in his everyday life including his cat and partner John F. Sheehy.
  - Sketches and Preliminary Studies, circa 1960-2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Oversized Sketches and Preliminary Studies, circa 1960-2000; Archival Resource Key (Box OV 7)
- Sketchbooks, circa 1955-1990; Series 7; Archival Resource Key; 0.9 Linear feet Box 2-4
  Twelve sketchbooks date from circa 1955-1990 and are filled with hundreds of sketches in pencil, charcoal, and watercolor. Some sketches illustrate Clutz's preparatory thinking for finished works and others were completed as part of a technical demonstration in one of his courses. Subjects range from exterior to domestics scenes to portraits. A few pages contain logistical notes pertaining to his courses.
  - Sketchbook, 1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Sketchbook, 1955-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Sketchbook, circa 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Sketchbook, circa 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Sketchbook, circa 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Sketchbook, circa 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Sketchbook, circa 1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Sketchbook, circa 1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Sketchbook, circa 1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Sketchbook, circa 1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Sketchbook, circa 1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Sketchbook, circa 1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 4)